<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Certain material and useful considerations about the laws positive and laws of necessity relating to the unhappy distractions of the present times</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 32 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50269</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1288A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R36494</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15703608</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 15703608</idno>
            <idno type="VID">104471</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50269)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 104471)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1152:64)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Certain material and useful considerations about the laws positive and laws of necessity relating to the unhappy distractions of the present times</title>
                  <author>Mathew, John.</author>
                  <author>Philalethes.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 13 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Wing attributes work to John Mathew, which name is written on t.p. in manuscript.</note>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Philalethes.</note>
                  <note>Title has been changed by ms. note to read: ... relating to the unhappy distractions of [ye] the[n] present times [1643/4]</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament --  History.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1660-1688.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:104471:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:104471:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Certain <hi>MATERIAL</hi> and <hi>USEFUL</hi> CONSIDERATIONS ABOUT The Laws Poſitive, AND Laws of Neceſſity, RELATING To the unhappy DISTRACTIONS of the preſent TIMES.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2 COR.</hi> XIII. <hi>Verſ. 8.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>We can do nothing againſt the Truth, but for the Truth.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 THES.</hi> V. <hi>Verſ. 21, 22.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Prove all things, hold faſt that which is good; abſtain from all appearance of Evil.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>JAM.</hi> III. <hi>Verſ. 17, 18.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>The Wiſdom that is from above, is firſt pure, then peaceable, gentle, and eaſie to be entreated, full of Mercy and good Fruits, without partiality, and without hypocriſie.</p>
               <p>And the Fruit of Righteouſneſs is ſown in peace of them that make peace.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed at LONDON, in the Year 1680.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:104471:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:104471:2"/>
            <head>TO HIS REVEREND FRIEND THEODIDACTUS.</head>
            <p>HAving been much troubled, even to reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſneſs in my Thoughts, about the tender and dangerous Diſtractions of theſe Times, I have often and earneſtly beſought Almighty God in my Prayers that he would aſſiſt me with his Spirit, that I might honeſtly ſet my ſelf to ſeek the Truth, ſo ſeeking that I might find it, and finding it, may chearfully embrace it, and conſtantly cleave unto it, in what Caſe or Danger ſoever I ſhould find it.</p>
            <p>To this end I tasked my ſelf to the ſaddeſt and ſevereſt Meditations my weak Body and Intellectuals could undergo, which being, I truſt by the guidance of God, reſolved into theſe enſuing Hypotheſes, I commit to your judicious and moſt impartial Cenſure, being not ſo fond of mine own fancies, but that I can indure to ſee them ſtript ſtark naked; and if they prove not the Iſſues of Truth, to diſinherit them from ever having farther poſſeſſion of my Thought: I ſee not many things, and hear not all, living ſo remote from any Town where the Tide of Books and Reports flows in; ſome Pamphlets there are walking about with as much confidence, and finding as good
<pb facs="tcp:104471:3"/>entertainment as Truth it ſelf needeth, and with a great deal of leſs Modeſty than it uſeth to do <hi>Pleas, Appeals, Reaſons, &amp;c.</hi> which, beg the Queſtion I look they ſhould prove, left me more unſatisfied (rather) than they found me: I have hitherto (perhaps through fondneſs) more contentment from theſe Conceptions of mine own, which I intreat you to examin with all Faithfulneſs and Severity, as knowing you cannot do your ſelf or me greater injury than to flatter me in falſhood, who am come (praiſed be God) ſo far towards Wiſdom, as heartily to thank him who rebukes me in Love, and lovingly to thank him who refutes me with Reaſon.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>PHILALETHES.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:104471:3"/>
            <p n="1">1. ALthough the King and Parliament aſſembled together are the moſt Honourable and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Court of the Kingdom, from whom there is no humane appeal, yet they are ſtill to be look'd upon as a Company of <hi>Men,</hi> ſubject to <hi>Infirmities, Paſſions,</hi> and <hi>Errors,</hi> as other men are, and therefore may (even were they concur) determin things Evil in themſelves. Or elſe we muſt grant that no Parliament Acts were ever Evil in themſelves, and ſo needed no Abrogation, but only inconvenient for Time and Occaſions, and ſo needed but ſuſpenſions, 'till fit Seaſons reinforceing them might return; and if the whole may err in their Determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, much more may the parts ſeverally, and alone.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In ſo great a Number, it is probable there ſtill will be (as it is certain now there are) ſome of green Years, ſlender Parts, and ſmall Experience, little or no Learning either in Arts or Law; and I may add (from the Cenſures of ſome part of that Court upon the other) of (at leaſt) <hi>ſuſpected Integrity,</hi> who as they are Choſen by popular Voices, (wherein ſiniſter references often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times bear no ſmall ſway) ſo are they probably led in Voting by popular Arguments tending moſt to Liberty, being incompetent Judges of the Methods and Myſteries of State-Government: Whence it will follow, that where the number of Voices, and not the depth of Argument, carries it; the fitteſt and juſteſt Propoſitions may oft be overborn by Number, which cannot be confuted by Reaſon.</p>
            <p n="3">3. As it is true, that no Evil ought to be imagined of the Parliament, ſo it is as true, that none ought to be imagined of the King; and yet it is not untrue, that
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:104471:4"/>where there is none, the greateſt Evil may be ſuſpected; and the greateſt may be, where none is imagined.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Though no Evil ought to be imagined in the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>conjunctim,</hi> and in the Lump, <hi>viz.</hi> That what the King and both Houſes ſhall fairly and freely conclude, and Enact, will prejudice no man; yet in regard of the particular Members, when I know Evil by them, I may ſuſpect Evil from them: Elſe, why doth one part of the Parliament, not only ſuſpect, but ſay ſo much and ſo great Evil of the other, whilſt they mutually repute each other <hi>Enemies of the State,</hi> which of all civil Evils is the <hi>greateſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Where there is a noiſe of <hi>Extream danger</hi> (which all men fear) and as earneſt an undertaking for preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (which all men deſire), it is eaſie to conceive how ready men will aſſent, without a due Examination, either of the imminency of the danger, or lawfulneſs of the prevention, eſpecially men of the weaker ſort, not able ſo well to judge of either.</p>
            <p n="6">6. When it is poſſible, that no one in either Houſe of Parliament may be Learned in the Law, ſince Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Knights, Gentlemen, Citizens, and Townſmen, (of which they conſiſt) are not neceſſary to be ſo, nor one more than another: I ſee not how the judgment of the Law can fully and properly reſide in them, eſpecially when the King conſents not. And ſo much ſeems im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed by the ſetting of the Judges in the Lords Houſe, who (for ought I hear) have no other Office there, but to adviſe, or advertiſe in point of Law.</p>
            <p n="7">7. When it is ſaid, the Judgment of the major part of both Houſes is the judgment of the whole Parliament, and conſequently of the Kingdom, I conceive it is not rightly affirmed; for beſides, that the Judgment of the Clergy is not (ſo much as in a ſhadow) there repreſented (who are a conſiderable part of the Kingdom, and ſhould be preſumed to have as good judgment, and be as good men, as others.) I reſign not my <hi>Judgment,</hi> but promiſe
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:104471:4"/>
               <hi>Obedience</hi> to the <hi>Parliament,</hi> not barely to the Burgeſſes of my own Town (whom perhaps I think very unfit) and who were choſen againſt my will, but to the Reſult and Determination of both Houſes, and not to them only neither, but as all are allowed, confirmed, and perfected, by the King's aſſent. For I am repreſented in the Commons but as ſubordinate to the King, and to joyn with the King, and with the Lords (not with, or againſt both, or either of them) to make Laws for the good of the Kingdom. So that when the Act is made by the concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of all the three Requiſit Conſents, then (as I ſuppoſe, and <hi>not till then</hi>) it becomes Obligatory, and (as a peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Subject) I muſt obey it, if it be lawful before God, though my judgment be ſtill free at home, and I do think it inexpedient, as the Negative part of the Votes do, for it is impoſſible, and againſt <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Nature,</hi> that any underſtanding Man's judgment, back'd with ſtrength of Argument, ſhould be led Captive by two or three Votes.</p>
            <p n="8">8. The major part of the Houſes being the part which exceeds the other but by three or four Voices; ſhall not that Law, which is concluded only by the advantage of thoſe Voices without the King's conſent, be a <hi>Lesbian</hi> Rule, or Noſe of Wax, which upon a ſecond Vote may paſs the contrary way upon a caſual abſence, or preſence, of ſo ſmall a Number? The Law is a ſtreight Rule, and always like it ſelf; if ſuch and ſuch a thing be <hi>Law</hi> after it was ſo Voted by the major part of the Houſes, it was <hi>Law</hi> before it was ſo Voted (unleſs an abſolute Power of Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>making be in ſuch a Vote) and then may be put in Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion without new Voting, only the Law ought to be produced. If the major part of the Votes of both Houſes be only <hi>Declarative</hi> of the Law, then in reaſon the firſt Voting ſhould ſtand, or elſe this would be a very uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Rule, and ſo the caſe of ordering the <hi>Militia</hi> ſhould not be according to Law, becauſe that was firſt (and twice) Countervoted by the Houſe of Lords. Such broad
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:104471:5"/>and obvious exceptions ought (in matters of ſo high con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment) to be fully cleared and removed.</p>
            <p n="9">9. When the Queſtion is, who ſhall be Judge of the Law, I ſuppoſe it muſt be meant, either of the ſence of particular Laws, or of the Latitude and ſcope of the Laws in general. If of the firſt, I conceive the ſence will appear, 1. Either by the clear Light that it hath in it ſelf (as the Sun ſhews his own Light). Or, 2. By reference to other Laws or Clauſes touching the ſame Argument, which are more perſpicuous. Or, 3. By the uſage and practice, which is the life of the Laws. If none of theſe can make it plain, in my judgment it becomes no Law, but is Obſolete until a full ſence be agreed upon again, by the full Authority that firſt made the Law. Otherwiſe I ſee not any Rule for declaring of the <hi>Law,</hi> that can be always abſolutely determinative; for (beſides that the ſame thing is at divers times diverſly Voted) if Votes of either Houſe ſhould chance (as poſſibly they may) to be equally divided, and the major part of both Houſes ſeverally, be neceſſarily required to determin, where ſhall the Determination be, when the Votes of One at leaſt be equally ballanced? Unleſs we fly unto a third way, <hi>viz.</hi> That the major part of both Houſes in Groſs, where the exception lies as full, becauſe they may chance to be equal alſo. If it be underſtood of the ſecond, then that Latitude ought to be evinced from ſome Terms in the Law expreſſed (which terms are to be produced) and not from the pleaſure of any that ſhall ſay, That is lawful which ſeems ſo to them, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally when they make themſelves the ſole Judges, both of Law and Equity. For whether will not ſuch a Liberty reach? A Tranſition is ſo made <hi>à Genere ad Genus,</hi> from <hi>Poſitive Law,</hi> to the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and that being various, according to the diverſity of Apprehenſions, cannot be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed upon all, where the full Legiſlative Power is not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>current. And I conceive it is not properly ſaid, <hi>That in extreme danger, I may by Law do that, which otherwiſe I may
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:104471:5"/>not do.</hi> But, <hi>in ſuch a Caſe, I may do that, and be excuſed, which by Law I cannot do.</hi> As in an Aſſault, I think the Law does not ſay, <hi>You may kill a Man,</hi> or take away his Weapon, but <hi>if you do it, the Law will not puniſh you;</hi> becauſe it is againſt all Reaſon, that where the Law affords me no help, it ſhould not hold me excuſed for helping my ſelf, when Neceſſity (which <hi>hath no Law</hi>) is ſo preſſing, that otherwiſe I muſt periſh.</p>
            <p n="10">10. When <hi>Neceſſity</hi> and <hi>Extreme Danger,</hi> are made the Grounds for (otherwiſe) doubtful and dangerous Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takings, it were meet thoſe Terms were rightly defined, that ſo we might clearly ſee the ſoundneſs of our War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant. I conceive that to be, <hi>when a Man is ſo preſently diſtreſt, that he can make no poſſible uſe of any poſitive Law to help him;</hi> and ſo becomes in a ſort diſoblig'd from it, and left free to the Law of Nature, which permits every things to ſeek the Preſervation of it ſelf. This Neceſſity diſpenſes with ordinary Duties, both to God and Man; but we muſt be ſure of the <hi>Neceſſity</hi> before we aſſume the <hi>Liberty.</hi> If a Man ſteal, and plead Neceſſity, he ſhall not be excuſed, becauſe the Law hath not left him remedileſs in his Wants. I may not take another Man's Sword from him, becauſe I have reaſon to fear he will hurt me; nor the Sword I have lent one, though he have threatened to kill me, ſo long as he draws it not upon me, becauſe I have a Remedy yet by Law, and may bind him to the Peace, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (Then much leſs may I wreſt His that hath ſworn to defend me.) When Neceſſity is but ſuppoſed, that there is no ſimple and abſolute Neceſſity is confeſt; and therefore no Law is (under pretence of Neceſſity) yet to be violated. The Kingdom may be in danger, and the Danger <hi>not extreme,</hi> nor any Neceſſity <hi>ſuch,</hi> but that it may be preſerved by ordinary Defence; or if the Danger be urgent, we may not ſeek to prevent that <hi>without Law,</hi> which <hi>by Law</hi> is well provided for already. In great Dangers, (ſuch as are now <hi>ſuppoſed</hi>) the Kingdom is to be put into a Poſture of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, againſt Invaſion, domeſtick Rebellion, or Tumult:
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:104471:6"/>By Law and Cuſtom the King is to order it: And ſo much is acknowledged by the preſent Parliament, in their Reply to the King's Anſwer the 29th of <hi>January,</hi> (if it be theirs) when ſpeaking of the Forts and Caſtles of the Kingdom, they have theſe Words, <hi>viz. We confeſs the Nomination of any Perſon to thoſe Places ſo principal and inſeparable a Flower of the Crown, veſted in You, and derived to You from Your Anceſtors by the Fundamental Laws of the Kingdom, You may reſerve to Your Self.</hi> And anon after, ſpeaking of the <hi>Militia,</hi> they ſay, <hi>Which Militia alſo We acknowledge by the Law is ſubject to no Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, but of Your Majeſty, and of Authority derived from You.</hi> Now he carefully applying himſelf to it, I ſee not what <hi>Neceſſity</hi> or <hi>diſobliging Extremity</hi> can be alledged to diſpoſſeſs him of it. When he is not <hi>convinced</hi> to have failed in his Duty; to doubt that he will, is not to prove <hi>that he hath,</hi> but rather that <hi>he hath not</hi> done it. If the Enemies were landed, and the Subject aſſaulted, (which are many de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees beyond the Dangers when this fell firſt into Debate) the Ordering of the Defence would be ſtill in the King, (unleſs where particular Outrages inforce particular Places, for the Defence of themſelves, by the <hi>Law of Neceſſity,</hi> which out-weighs other Laws:) But if the King be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardleſs of his Truſt, and their Safety, and lets the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies graze along his Kingdom: Or if any of his Miniſters prove falſe to the State, and either take part with a Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign, or become themſelves a Home-Enemy, and the King ſtrive not to ſuppreſs them, or (all which far be it to imagin) do animate and invite them to diſpoil his good Subjects; <hi>then</hi> (and, for ought I know, <hi>not till then</hi>) is the Danger in Extremity, and then is the firſt Plea for the Laws of Neceſſity, which do not only enable the State in common, but every Man in particular, to ſeek the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of himſelf and his Country, by all ſuch ways as ſtand not in oppoſition to the Laws of God.</p>
            <p n="11">11. When I <hi>proteſt</hi> to defend the Powers and Privileges in Parliaments, it is but <hi>ſo far as lawfully I may,</hi> and <hi>ſo far as I know them,</hi> or ought to know them, being eaſie to be
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:104471:6"/>known, <hi>viz.</hi> ſuch as by Cuſtom and unanimous Conſent have obtained, as unqueſtionable; not ſuch as are que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtioned amongſt themſelves, ſome claiming, and others gain-ſaying; nor ſuch as are challenged <hi>without or againſt the King,</hi> whom, being Head of the Parliament, ought to have Conſent in the concluding of Privileges, much leſs ought he to be unprivileged, without his Conſent, whoſe Privileges are <hi>proteſted for</hi> (as well as, and) with the reſt, and the Defence whereof ſworn to in the Oath of Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy; where we ſwear <hi>to our power to aſſiſt and defend all Juriſdiction, and Privileges, and Preheminences, and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities, granted or belonging to the King's Highneſs, his Heirs,</hi> &amp;c. If the diſpoſing of the Forts, Navy, Magazines, and Militia be (as it is confeſſed they are) by the Law of the Land the <hi>Privileges of the King,</hi> there can be <hi>no diſtinction</hi> (to my apprehenſion) <hi>imagined</hi> upon any <hi>Fears or Jealouſies whatſoever,</hi> (when no Evils by him are actually practiſed, and all Intentions of Evil are abſolutely abjured) to war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant any Men (few or more) in Parliament or out of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament (who have taken that Oath) to diſpoſſeſs him of them, or detein them from him, in <hi>what manner ſoever he ſhall come to demand them:</hi> For the Oath is peremptory and unlimitted, and <hi>non eſt diſtinguendum, ubi Lex non diſtinguit.</hi> To ſay they are deteined <hi>for him,</hi> (not <hi>from him</hi>) might have ſome colour, if the King were either a Child, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted, or weak-minded; but to an adult and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding Prince, ſuch a pretence is an higher derogation, as diſparaging his Wiſdom and Fidelity.</p>
            <p n="12">12. Where Power is inveſted in any, and by Cuſtom and free Conſent is made Hereditary, I conceive it cannot afterwards be <hi>limitted</hi> with other Conditions than at firſt was agreed on, without the Conſent of him that hath it.</p>
            <p n="13">13. That which is certainly lawful, and but doubtfully dangerous, is to be choſen rather than that which is <hi>not certainly lawful,</hi> but is <hi>doubtfully dangerous.</hi> When a Man offers no Violence, though (upon good reaſon) I fear he will hurt me, to let his Sword alone is <hi>certainly lawful,</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:104471:7"/>though <hi>doubtfully dangerous;</hi> but to wreſt it from him, when he offers no Aſſault, is not <hi>certainly lawful,</hi> but rather <hi>certainly unlawful,</hi> and but <hi>doubtfully ſafe,</hi> or rather <hi>undoubtedly dangerous;</hi> for by that occaſion a Quarrel is made, and Blood ſhed, which might otherwiſe (poſſibly at leaſt) have been ſaved. Would the Application were not eaſie.</p>
            <p n="14">14. If a Man being illegally diſpoſſeſt of his Right, do (in <hi>Heat of Contention</hi>) uſe ſome illegal Means for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of it, that is not to be drawn into Argument to juſtifie the Illegality of the firſt Uſurpation. If a Man unaſſaulted wreſt my Sword from me, and I <hi>afterwards</hi> beat him, he may not draw <hi>mine</hi> after-beating into Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to juſtifie <hi>his</hi> taking my Sword from me.</p>
            <p n="15">15. When the Envy of Not yielding to the Advice of his Great Council, is caſt upon the King, it is firſt fit to ſet the Cauſe upon its own Legs. It ſeems by many paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages in theſe <hi>Obſervations,</hi> and other Books, and by more than Book-paſſages, that the King is eſteemed a <hi>Tyrant</hi> over his People; for what elſe is implied in diſtruſting and vilepending of his Oaths, Obteſtations, Impreca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions? in imputing the Attendants, and Company he has about him, (whom he owns and protects) <hi>Enemies to the State?</hi> in raiſing (at leaſt defenſive) Arms? in ſeizing his Navy? ſhutting the Town-gates againſt him? and the poſſeſſing of his Forts and Magazines againſt his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand? For will a Man wreſt another's Sword from him, if he dod not preſume he will draw it upon him? Nay, is it lawful to take any Man's Sword, (if not every Body's, then not His) 'till it be drawn upon him, or ſome violence offer'd him? If it be ſaid, <hi>then it is too late;</hi> it may as well be ſaid, <hi>'till then it is too ſoon.</hi> Now then, when they are ſo opinioned and jealous of the King's Love and Fidelity, how can it be imagined, that he ſhould look on them as ingenuous and equal Counſellors, and not be as diſtruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of the Sincerity of their Advices? For, how ſhall I perſuade another to be directed by me, as his Friend, when I give him to underſtand, that I take him for mine Enemy
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:104471:7"/>that intends Miſchief againſt me? Eſpecially where the Matter is not of ordinary Concernment, wherein each one's Rights are left free and untouch'd, but ſuch as trench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth deep into his Majeſty's <hi>Prerogative,</hi> and tendeth not only to the reſtraining his Power, but mainly alſo to the quenching of his Honour, whilſt by yielding to ſuch Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, he muſt <hi>tacitly confeſs</hi> that he is not fit to be truſted, and (by conſequence) <hi>openly proclaim</hi> that he is not worthy to be King.</p>
            <p n="16">16. If the (ſo called) Malignant Party ſhould chance to be the prevailing Party in the Houſe, (as the King puts the Caſe in his Anſwer to the Declaration of the 26th of <hi>May, pag.</hi> 8.) and ſhould alledge, <hi>That through the precipitancy of ſome Mens pretended Zeal, the Kingdom were like to run into confuſion,</hi> (for ſuch a Caſe may be, and <hi>Conſpiracy for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Reformation</hi> was the Title and Argument of a Book many years ſince) muſt theſe be ſafely ſecured? And preſuming the King favours that ſide, and the other Party not liking the courſe that he will take to ſecure the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, ſhould vote it lawful for them to do it themſelves without him, muſt this preſently be concluded to be the Judgment of the whole Kingdom, and to be <hi>according to Law,</hi> when no Law can be produced? and the King to be ill affected to his beſt Subjects? or to be miſlead by evil Counſellors, to undo Himſelf and his Kingdom, by not yielding to the Advice of his Great Council? Or, Will the adverſe Party take it well to be reputed <hi>Enemies to the State,</hi> a <hi>Malignant Party, &amp;c?</hi> And if not, it were but meet, that the ſubſtantial Differences of the Caſe were ſo well opened, that they that deſire to know what is Juſt and Right, might tell where to find it: And that all Men (of moderate Capacity, Judgment, and Ingenuity) might ſee clearly the Infallibility of One Party, and the Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie of the Other.</p>
            <p n="17">17. When the Forts, Navy, Magazines, Offices, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are ſaid to be intruſted in the King, or the King intruſted with them <hi>for the Good of the Kingdom,</hi> the ſence of the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:104471:8"/>Word [Intruſted] in this place would be well to be cleared. Not to queſtion, Whether the King have thoſe things by way of <hi>Truſt from the People?</hi> it will be of all granted (as it is by the King himſelf) That <hi>God and the Law have truſted him with them,</hi> and that for the <hi>good</hi> of the Kingdom; and ſo / to employ them, he is further tyed to by his Oath: But there is a twofold Truſt; one, that is <hi>abſolute</hi> and <hi>unlimitted,</hi> otherwiſe than that the End is ſpecified, ſuppoſed, or preſumed; (the End not ſo much <hi>limitting</hi> the Truſt, as the Truſt <hi>denoting</hi> and <hi>implying</hi> the End;) and there is a Truſt <hi>conditional,</hi> or <hi>circumſcribed</hi> in ſuch ſort, that to fail in the performance is to <hi>forfeit</hi> the Truſt. The firſt gives a Man Right to the <hi>Thing</hi> intruſted, the ſecond gives only a Right to the <hi>Truſt</hi> of the Thing. I conceive the King's Truſt is of the firſt kind; who being preſumed to mean all Good to his People, according to the Maxim in Politics, <hi>No Evil ought to be imagined by the King,</hi> hath theſe things frankly and abſolutely committed to his Government and Diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, and howſoever he ſhall order them, I ſuppoſe he is accountable to no Man, nor queſtionable by any, unleſs he clearly, and publicly, and undoubtedly diſpoſe of them to the Ruin of his Kingdom, and ſo puts the People to an <hi>evident</hi> Extremity, or <hi>lawleſs</hi> Neceſſity. If there be any <hi>Limits,</hi> the Law ſhould expreſs them, for he being <hi>Supreme,</hi> there is no other Power to impoſe them. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are the Actions of his Miniſters to be cenſured, unleſs by them the known Laws have been violated.</p>
            <p>If this Truſt ſhould be Managed or <hi>Regulated</hi> by Both Houſes of Parliament, firſt, That Power ſhould be made appear to the King and People; and then there muſt be either a <hi>Standing Court</hi> of Parliament, or elſe the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment muſt be called ſo often as the King ſhall have occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to ſend out Ships, take in, or put out Powder and Ammunition into his Magazines, chuſe any Officers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which were abſurd to conceive.</p>
            <p>If any Man, having confidence in <hi>his</hi> Friend, ſhould ſay to him, <hi>Sir, I will freely give my Eſtate into your hands,</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:104471:8"/>only <hi>you ſhall ſwear you will be a Father to my Children:</hi> Here is an Implication of a Truſt, yet a clear Right in the <hi>Thing;</hi> ſo that he may Let or Set, Build or Pull down, Give or Lend, and yet be <hi>accountable to none,</hi> nor <hi>falſifie his Truſt,</hi> ſo long as the Children want nothing. Yea, and if he fail of the Truſt, perhaps ſome Court of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience may relieve them; but I believe no poſitive Law can controll him.</p>
            <p>The Caſe is other with Feoffees, or Executors in Truſt, who have a Right <hi>only</hi> to the <hi>Truſt,</hi> and <hi>none</hi> to the <hi>Thing</hi> intruſted, which is only the Heirs, the Poor's, or Legato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of him by whom it was bequeathed.</p>
            <p n="18">18. The King's and Subjects Intereſts are mutual, he refers to every Subject, and every Subject to Him, as the Line <hi>from</hi> the Center <hi>to</hi> the Circle; and what Intereſt he hath in One, he hath in Another, and in All, as well as in Any; and His Intereſt in them is of a higher Alloy, more Noble, (as <hi>Command</hi> is, than <hi>Subjection,</hi>) the Intereſt of Protection is mutual, the Odds is, that All the People are not more worth than the King, but the King and People more worth than either.</p>
            <p n="19">19. Perſonal Differences of Wiſdom or Folly, Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs or Strength, Courage or Cowardize, Meanneſs or Excellency of Parts or Arts, make no Difference in the Right of the King, though they ſhew a great Difference in God's dealing with the Kingdom.</p>
            <p n="20">20. When a King plays the Tyrant, or Uſurper upon his People's juſt Liberties, I conceive it muſt either be, firſt, by a <hi>violent Suppreſſion</hi> of Old Laws and Cuſtoms yet in force; or ſecondly, by a <hi>wilful Obſtruction</hi> of Known Laws by force; or thirdly, by <hi>wicked Oppreſſion</hi> by force without Law. When therefore Tyranny is imputed to, or implied in a Prince, (of whom we ought not ſlightly to think any Evil) it will become Chriſtians <hi>throughly</hi> to examin upon <hi>what point</hi> he is convinced, and not take up <hi>ſuch</hi> Reports upon whole-ſale, and in groſs.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:104471:9"/>
            <p n="21">21. If the King have not a <hi>Negative Voice,</hi> he ſeems not to have ſo much Power in Parliamentary Acts as a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Burgeſs; for if the Votes be even before, His may be the Caſting Voice of the Houſe, and I ſee not ſo much as a <hi>Vote</hi> allowed His Majeſty.</p>
            <p n="22">22. When the King ſhall think it fit, not to give his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to what the major part of the Houſe ſhall agree upon, He is not barely to be conſidered as <hi>One Man againſt ſo Many;</hi> for (beſides His Privy-Council at hand, Men accuſtomed to, and experienced in Matters of State, and beſides, that poſſibly a very great Number of Both Houſes are alſo of the King's Mind) we are to conſider the King, as One beſt acquainted with the Rules and Myſteries of Government, being as it were the Trade to (and in) which he hath been born, bred, and brought up, and therefore is preſumed to ſee farther into it than many others together, not ſo acquinted with the Myſtery: For (beſides that God hath a ſpecial way of communicating Wiſdom to Kings, in which regard, <hi>A wiſe Sentence is</hi> ſaid to be <hi>the Lips of the King,</hi> Prov. xv. 10. and <hi>The Heart of a King is unſearchable,</hi> Prov. xxv. 3.) Hiſtories make it plain, that there are <hi>Arcana Imperii (&amp; Militiae)</hi> which the King (and Captains) apprehend, which a thouſand do not, and which perhaps may not be fit for all Men (nay, not for any Man elſe) to know. When an adult, and a prudent Prince ſhall own, and approve of, and protect ſuch and ſuch perſons, as his tryed Friends, and known Councellors; if any, under what pretence ſoever of their ſuppoſed ſuggeſting evil Councel (when no evil practices are apparent, yea, when ſuch Practices and Councels are utterly diſavowed and abjured by the King) ſhall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume not only without the King's conſent, but againſt <hi>his expreſs Commands</hi> to <hi>take up Arms,</hi> and to deſtroy and take off ſuch perſons, though no Evil be intended againſt his perſon (and yet who can tell what is in his mind that comes towards a Man with a drawn Sword in his hand?) I ſee not what diſtinction can help, but that ſuch Arms
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:104471:9"/>are taken (not for, but) againſt the King: Otherwiſe how can any thing be ſaid to be <hi>Againſt God?</hi> Who being inviola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in his Perſon, cannot otherwiſe be reſiſted than by the blaſpheming of his Name, breaking his Commands, rejecting his Motions, proſecuting and perſecuting his Servants, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="23">23. When it is ſaid, the <hi>King was made for the People,</hi> and not the People for the King; (beſides, that the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon is as idle, as that of the Members <hi>Againſt the Belly,</hi> in the Apologue, and the Apoſtle hath met with it, 1 Cor. xii. It is alſo not abſolutely true, for <hi>The King was no more made a Man for Others,</hi> than <hi>They for Him,</hi> not made a King more <hi>for the Good and Safety of the People,</hi> than <hi>They were put into ſuch a poſture of Obedience, and Order, that He might be ſafe, as well as they;</hi> yea, <hi>rather than Any</hi> (if not than Many) <hi>of them,</hi> as being ſuppoſed the Chiefeſt amongſt them.) The ſence, in which it ſeems beſt to hold, is, <hi>That the King</hi> was made for the need, and neceſſity of the People, and not They for His, <hi>viz.</hi> He can more ſecurely be no King, than They can be without a King. And he takes the <hi>Surrender of their Power,</hi> with their dependances and conſequences, not as a kindneſs from Them, but as doing a kindneſs to Them, as is implied in the Refuſal of the Vine, Fig-Tree, and Olive-Trees, in <hi>Jotham</hi>'s Parable, Judg. ix. 7. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and the Story of <hi>Jeptha,</hi> Judg. xi. 4. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for, on Him they unload their Cares and Fears, who foregoes His own Eaſe and Quiet, that He may procure it for His People: Himſelf taking Care that All Men elſe may live without Care. Now, on Whom the neceſſity lyeth moſt, on them lyeth the Greateſt Obligation and Reſpect, There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore St. <hi>Paul</hi> requires <hi>Giving of Thanks for Kings,</hi> 1 Tim. ii. 2. So we may ſay of a Captain, a Pilot, a School-Maſter, a Phyſitian, that they were made for the need of their Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relates, which ſhould render them more Honourable, and rather draw <hi>Reſpects to them,</hi> than Challenge <hi>Greater Obſervances from them.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>Judge Righteous Judgment.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
